<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>cogitare</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2025-02-23T10:42:11+00:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Rohan</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Growing out of the consumption trap</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/23/consumption"/>
   <updated>2025-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2025/02/23/Consumption</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;maybe-mom-dad-are-right-it-is-the-phone&quot;&gt;Maybe mom, dad are right; it is the phone.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been feeling dependent on &lt;em&gt;consumption&lt;/em&gt;. What I mean is, there is a constant need to feed my brain with information, important or not, while not working for it. There is a need for instant gratification. Creativity is being suppressed. I am constantly looking for answers everywhere else, but not taking a step back and looking within. I cannot speak for all, but I know for a fact that majority of the world falling victim to the same consumption trap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;not-thinking-anymore&quot;&gt;Not thinking anymore&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember the time when I was young, maybe ten to twelve years ago, when young Rohan had nothing better to do, I’d just take a sheet of paper and start painting something. I had this mindless obsession where I would just sit for hours losing track of time doing things that felt, in hindsight, therapeutic. I used to love building things, like structures out of legos, cardboard, etc. I distinctly remember creating a diamond sword (from Minecraft), and a Fire Smasher (Power Rangers Samurai). All of these experiences I would probably never have if I was born a few years in the future. I was free back then. Even the times I would use my PC, which I had access to since I was four years old, it didnt interest me to watch videos all day and &lt;em&gt;consume&lt;/em&gt; content. I had the curious tendency to tinker with configurations of games and applications, play around with websites I made, all things which forced me into getting my hands dirty and express my &lt;em&gt;creativity&lt;/em&gt;. Now, due to everything being digitized, and the amount of captivating short-form content online, I feel an urge to constantly check my phone, to the point where it is the only thing I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person’s mind is dependent on constant inflow of external information, consuming as much content as possible without having the need to analyze and reflect even for a second. Modern media, which is so focused on shorter, attention grabbing content, as if spoonfeeding and chewing the food for another person just to swallow it, has directly contributed to the inability of creative thinking; or thinking in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;modern-media---the-bad-outweighs-the-good&quot;&gt;Modern media - the bad outweighs the good&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both consumption and creation are important. Learning from the experiences of other people is as important as being by yourself and reflecting. What matters is the type of content that is being consumed. Reading is a form of consumption as well, and there is a cognitive effort to concentrate and contemplate, indirectly helping improve creativity by introducing new perspectives. Movies, I believe, are an entertaining form of learning culture and history. Music calms the soul. There is no doubt that there are good sources of entertainment. Of course, moderation matters, but that is irrelevant to this discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The progress of humanity has always led to reduction of human effort as much as possible. But going after the mind is vicious. Mental exercise is key for the mind to grow, and the lesser effort the mind puts in, the lazier it will get. This has dangerous implications. A lazy mind leads to loss of creativity, originality and drive. The way short-form content works is exactly this. It is just one piece of media after the other, continuous stream of information, with no breaks to process it, with no purpose, just random bits of information that is interesting and will captivate the mind using instant gratification. These bits of information, unlikely to be remembered a few minutes after watching it, is just information overload. The mind loses focus, serves no purpose, and gradually becomes dependent on this to even function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;education-and-technology&quot;&gt;Education and technology&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of spending time figuring a thing out from scratch is now considered time wasted, probably because there is an answer for everything. The growing consensus is against ‘reinventing the wheel’. Information is universal, owing to the massive surge in Internet access. The Open-source movement has also been a huge contributor to providing access to resources that are a treasure trove of information. The advancements in technology have certainly improved the quality of life, especially so in healthcare and science, but in education we have come to a point where it is beginning to do more harm than good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From schoolwork to university assigments, everything is just a search away. We find the exact question we want on some online forum. And even if we don’t, the next obvious step is to use LLMs. These LLMs now are so good that it can solve most undergraduate-level university questions with ease, at least in Science and Engineering. I would say it could do better than 95% of my class right now. Point is, we are not giving our brain breathing space to step back and think for a second. Of course, it is going to take a lot more time to get the answer you are looking for, but it opens up this creative pathway in your mind, where it makes you capable to think logically and reach to the answer or conclusion yourself. And this is the pathway to innovation. No matter how much these LLMs help you, it will never have a single original thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ingenuity is the beauty of the human mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;be-alone-and-think&quot;&gt;Be alone and think&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve blabbered about what and why consumption is bad, but what can be done about it? These are a few things that I have been trying to do-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Being alone&lt;/em&gt;. I mean absolutely alone. Sometimes I like to take a break from the world and just think. Think about where I’ve come from, my story so far, memories that I enjoy, memories that I didn’t. Everything. It just humbles me so much and motivates me to work on the present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“People talk to you a great deal about your education, but some good, sacred memory, preserved from childhood, is perhaps the best education.” - Dostoevsky, The Brothers Karamazov&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve noticed that as I grew older, my mind has been getting piled up and racing with thoughts all the time, so it’s a good idea to step back and reflect. I guess this is what meditation is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read more often, and have started to write, giving my brain a good workout, helping me think more. I believe expressing yourself, be it music, arts, writing, is an amazing way of opening up your mind and soul, and gives birth to inspiration and inventiveness in everyday life as well. Learning a new skill (in my case, writing) keeps you occupied and married to the journey of betterment, and helps to discover your true self in the process, and has definitely helped me reduce the need for mindless consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
